<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Swarm Lab</title>
    <description>Welcome to the Swarm Lab where we study Swarm Intelligence in natural and artificial systems.</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Fri, 15 Mar 2019 15:15:55 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 15 Mar 2019 15:15:55 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.7.4</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>New publication - &quot;Temporal and spatial pattern of trail clearing in the Australian meat ant, &lt;i&gt;Iridomyrmex purpureus&lt;/i&gt;&quot;</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The SwarmLab is happy to announce the publication of: &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.anbehav.2019.02.006&quot;&gt;Middleton, E. J. T., Garnier, S., Latty, T., and Reid, C. R. (2019). Temporal and spatial pattern of trail clearing in the Australian meat ant, &lt;em&gt;Iridomyrmex purpureus&lt;/em&gt;. Anim. Behav. 150, 97–111. doi:10.1016/j.anbehav.2019.02.006&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; Many ant species use trails to connect important resources. In addition, some ants actively clear obstacles from their trails. Although trail clearing is thought to be beneficial in decreasing travel time, the physical process of clearing requires an investment of time and energy. Given that trail clearing is a decentralized process, how do colonies decide when to invest in clearing? In this study, we examined trail clearing in the Australian meat ant, using artificial semipermeable barriers mimicking grass. We tested the hypothesis that investment in clearing was influenced by the abundance and physical toughness of obstacles and that the selection of which grass blade to cut was a nonrandom process that decreases travel distance. We found that low abundance/low toughness treatments experienced the greatest amount of clearing and high abundance/high toughness the least. Although ants did not clear an optimally efficient trail, the results of our percolation analysis support the inference that the ants strategically deployed clearing, taking multiple factors into account when deciding to invest in this strategy. The resultant clearing patterns provided shorter travel routes for foraging ants than would be expected by the random removal of obstacles.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/03/09/new-publication/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/03/09/new-publication/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Announcing the 4th Collaborative Workshop on Modeling Collective Behavior</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The SwarmLab is pleased to announce the 4th Collaborative Workshop on Modeling Collective Behavior, funded by the NSF OAC Public Access Initiative &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nsf.gov/awardsearch/showAward?AWD_ID=1838955&quot;&gt;grant #1838955&lt;/a&gt;. The goal of this workshop is to provide researchers coming from mathematics, physics, engineering and biology with experience in working collaboratively to model and analyze data produced by research in collective behavior. This year we are also including an interdisciplinary art/science project (see Project 4 below) that will use virtual reality to explore and interact with data and models of collective behaviors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All information about the workshop, including application instructions and deadline, can be found &lt;a href=&quot;/meetings/data_model_2019/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/data_model_2019/banner.png&quot; alt=&quot;banner&quot; class=&quot;full&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/03/01/data-model-2019/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/03/01/data-model-2019/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Data-Driven Modeling of Collective Behavior and Emergent Phenomena in Biology (DDM-Bio) - June 5-7, 2017</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The SwarmLab is happy to announce the workshop on “Data-Driven Modeling of Collective Behavior and Emergent Phenomena in Biology” (&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/search?q=%23DDMBio&amp;amp;src=typd&quot;&gt;#DDMBio&lt;/a&gt;) to be held at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.samsi.info/&quot;&gt;SAMSI&lt;/a&gt; (Research Triangle Park, NC), June 5-7, 2017.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Description&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Collective behavior and emergent phenomena often arise in complex adaptive systems. Understanding the mechanisms that underlie such processes is simultaneously challenging and important to developments in engineering, technology, and advancing basic knowledge in the science of biological systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This collaborative workshop is targeted for researchers and students with research interests in collective behavior and emergent phenomena in biology and its applications. The participants will be organized into interdisciplinary teams according to their interests and complementary skills. Each team will be tasked with exploring, analyzing and modeling original data sets provided by biologist attendees. The event will be similar in spirit to a hackathon in computer science, with the goal of finding new ways to understand the provided biological data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We emphasize that the workshop is meant to involve active participation with attendees working together across disciplines to solve problems in current research. In addition, regular debriefing sessions will be organized throughout the 3 days of the workshop in order for each team to provide updates to and receive feedback from the rest of the participants on their progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Organizing Committee:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://theswarmlab.com/&quot;&gt;Simon Garnier&lt;/a&gt;, Dept. of Biological Sciences, New Jersey Institute of Technology&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/site/jasonmgrahamus/&quot;&gt;Jason M. Graham&lt;/a&gt;, Dept. of Mathematics, University of Scranton**&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;application-information&quot;&gt;Application information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://duke.qualtrics.com/SE/?SID=SV_eyaNrivpvY48fv7&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; class=&quot;btn btn-info&quot; role=&quot;button&quot;&gt;Apply Here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Application Deadline is April 17, 2017.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The workshop will be limited to about 40 participants and funding support priority will be given to U.S. based researchers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Questions: &lt;a href=&quot;ddm-bio@samsi.info&quot;&gt;ddm-bio@samsi.info&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 14 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/2016/12/14/DDM-Bio/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/2016/12/14/DDM-Bio/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>We're Hiring! Tenure track position in &quot;Organismic Function, from Behavior to Ecology​&quot;</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As part of an ongoing expansion, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://biology.njit.edu/&quot;&gt;Department of Biological Sciences&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.njit.edu&quot;&gt;New Jersey Institute of Technology (NJIT)&lt;/a&gt; is looking to fill one or two new tenure-track faculty positions at the Assistant Professor level, beginning in 2017. We seek applicants with an interest and established record in bridging levels from systems or organismic function to behavior or ecology. Research areas can include - but are not limited to - ethology, microbiology, functional ecology, or evolution. Candidates will be expected to maintain an active, funded research program, supervise graduate students, and contribute to the overall success of the Department.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NJIT is a tier-one public research university located in Newark, NJ, with an emphasis on STEM subjects. The Department of Biological Sciences at NJIT currently consists of ten research faculty with expertise in neurobiology, sensory and motor systems, locomotion, collective behavior, and functional and spatial ecology. The Department is also Federated with neighboring &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncas.rutgers.edu/biology&quot;&gt;Rutgers-University Newark&lt;/a&gt;, adding colleagues in cellular neurobiology, cell signaling, genetics, systematics, evolution and ecology. The successful applicant will occupy customizable space in a newly renovated research facility. Duties will also include teaching introductory and upper-level undergraduate and graduate courses, depending on expertise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NJIT is an equal-opportunity employer. Applications from minorities and women are especially welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Applicants should upload a CV, a cover letter, and a statement of research interest at the following address: &lt;a href=&quot;http://njit.jobs/applicants/Central?quickFind=55733&quot;&gt;njit.jobs/applicants/Central?quickFind=55733&lt;/a&gt;. In addition, they should arrange for at least three references to send letters directly to Ms. Shamay Carty at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:carty@njit.edu&quot;&gt;carty@njit.edu&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All inquiries should be directed to Dr. Simon Garnier, at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:garnier@njit.edu&quot;&gt;garnier@njit.edu&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/2016/10/05/We-re-hiring/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/2016/10/05/We-re-hiring/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>We're Hiring! Tenure track position in &quot;Cell Biology, Physiology, Systems or Organismic Function​&quot;</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As part of an ongoing expansion, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://biology.njit.edu/&quot;&gt;Department of Biological Sciences&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.njit.edu&quot;&gt;New Jersey Institute of Technology (NJIT)&lt;/a&gt; is looking to fill one or two new tenure-track faculty positions at the Assistant Professor level, beginning in 2017. We seek applicants with an interest and established record in bridging levels from cell biology or physiology, to systems or organismic function. Research areas can include - but are not limited to - neurobiology, ethology, evolution, or development. Candidates will be expected to maintain an active, funded research program, supervise graduate students, and contribute to the overall success of the Department.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NJIT is a tier-one public research university located in Newark, NJ, with an emphasis on STEM subjects. The Department of Biological Sciences at NJIT currently consists of ten research faculty with expertise in neurobiology, sensory and motor systems, locomotion, collective behavior, and functional and spatial ecology. The Department is also Federated with neighboring &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncas.rutgers.edu/biology&quot;&gt;Rutgers-University Newark&lt;/a&gt;, adding colleagues in cellular neurobiology, cell signaling, genetics, systematics, evolution and ecology. The successful applicant will occupy customizable space in a newly renovated research facility. Duties will also include teaching introductory and upper-level undergraduate and graduate courses, depending on expertise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NJIT is an equal-opportunity employer. Applications from minorities and women are especially welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Applicants should upload a CV, a cover letter, and a statement of research interest at the following address: &lt;a href=&quot;http://njit.jobs/applicants/Central?quickFind=55732&quot;&gt;njit.jobs/applicants/Central?quickFind=55732&lt;/a&gt;. In addition, they should arrange for at least three references to send letters directly to Ms. Shamay Carty at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:carty@njit.edu&quot;&gt;carty@njit.edu&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All inquiries should be directed to Dr. Farzan Nadim, at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:farzan@njit.edu&quot;&gt;farzan@njit.edu&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/2016/10/05/We-re-hiring-2/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/2016/10/05/We-re-hiring-2/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Decision-making without a brain - Our new paper in Interface</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;How do organisms without brains make decisions? Most of life is brainless and the vast majority of organisms on Earth lack neurons altogether. Plants, fungi and bacteria must all cope with the same problem as humans – to make the best choices in a complex and ever-changing world or risk dying – without the help of a simple nervous system in many cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our lab in collaboration with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.richardpmann.com/&quot;&gt;Richard Mann&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.leeds.ac.uk/&quot;&gt;University of Leeds&lt;/a&gt;), &lt;a href=&quot;http://staffwww.dcs.shef.ac.uk/people/J.Marshall/james.html&quot;&gt;James Marshall&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sheffield.ac.uk/&quot;&gt;University of Sheffield&lt;/a&gt;) and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tanyalatty.com/&quot;&gt;Tanya Latty&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;http://sydney.edu.au/&quot;&gt;University of Sydney&lt;/a&gt;) recently studied this problem in the unicellular slime mold, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Physarum_polycephalum&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Physarum polycephalum&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a single-cell organism that can grow to several square meters in size. This giant cell, which typically lives in shady, cool and moist areas of temperate forests, spreads out to search its environment like an amoeba, extending oozy tendrils along the forest floor in search of its prey of fungi, bacteria and decaying vegetable matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neither plant, animal nor fungus, &lt;em&gt;P. polycephalum&lt;/em&gt; has become an unlikely candidate for studies of cognition, due to its spectacular problem-solving abilities. In recent studies, &lt;em&gt;Physarum&lt;/em&gt; has been shown to solve labyrinth mazes, make complicated trade-offs, anticipate periodic events, remember where it has been, construct transport networks that have similar efficiency to those designed by human engineers and even make irrational decisions – a capability that has long been viewed as a by-product of brain circuitry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this study, we examined the decision-making ability of slime mold using a test classically used in humans, birds and other brained organisms: the two-armed bandit problem, named for the infamous slot machine, or one-armed bandit. In a two-armed bandit problem, the subject has two levers to pull, each of which delivers a certain, randomly determined reward. One of the levers is more likely to deliver a higher reward overall, so the challenge for participants is to decide at what point to stop exploring both options and decide to exclusively exploit just the one option in order to maximize their payoff. The phenomenon is called the exploration-exploitation tradeoff and is relevant to more than just slot machines, applying to many situations, including investors picking start-up companies to back or drivers choosing a parking space. As such, it has become a classical tool for testing the decision-making abilities of humans and other animals, but it has never before been used on an organism without a brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We adapted the two-armed bandit test for slime mold by giving the organism the choice to explore two opposite directions. In each direction, the slime mold encountered discrete patches of food, more or less regularly distributed. One direction would contain more of these patches than the other. They then observed how far in each direction the slime mold would explore before switching to the exploitation of one of the two directions only. The results of these experiments demonstrate that slime mold compares the relative qualities of multiple options, most often choosing the direction with the higher overall concentration of food. It was able to sum up the number of food patches encountered in each direction, as well as the quantity of food present at each patch to make correct and adaptive decisions as to the direction it should move next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The slime mold’s decision-making algorithm can be mathematically described as a tendency to exploit environments in proportion to their reward experienced through past sampling. The algorithm is intermediate in computational complexity between simple, reactionary heuristics and calculation-intensive optimal performance algorithms, yet it has very good relative performance. While the biological substrate of the algorithm remains to be identified, this study provides insight into ancestral mechanisms of decision making and suggests that fundamental principles of decision making, information processing and even cognition are shared among diverse biological systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our study has appeared in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://rsif.royalsocietypublishing.org/content/13/119&quot;&gt;June edition&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://rsif.royalsocietypublishing.org/&quot;&gt;Journal of The Royal Society Interface&lt;/a&gt; and can be found &lt;a href=&quot;http://rsif.royalsocietypublishing.org/content/13/119/20160030&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;in open access&lt;/strong&gt; here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 19 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/2016/06/19/Decision-Making-Without-Brain/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/2016/06/19/Decision-Making-Without-Brain/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Lens of Time - Slime Lapse</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Our work on slime mold was recently featured in a mini-documentary by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.spinefilms.com/&quot;&gt;Spine Films&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;a href=&quot;http://biographic.com/&quot;&gt;bioGraphic&lt;/a&gt;, a new multimedia magazine produced by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.calacademy.org/&quot;&gt;California Academy of Sciences&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;video width=&quot;100%&quot; controls=&quot;controls&quot;&gt;
  &lt;source src=&quot;http://n2ps.storied.co/uploads/548ceb34b78402c4c1baadd636a132f4.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/video&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/2016/06/12/Lens-of-Time-Slime-Lapse/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/2016/06/12/Lens-of-Time-Slime-Lapse/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>David Hughes' lecture at NJIT</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hugheslab.com/&quot;&gt;David Hughes&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.psu.edu/&quot;&gt;Penn State&lt;/a&gt; will be our guest Tuesday, March 29. His lab has a fascinating research program, exploring the relationship between disease and behavior. In particular, their work focuses on understanding how and why parasites manipulate their host behavior, and on the role behavior plays in disease transmission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During his visit, David will also deliver a lecture as part of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncas.rutgers.edu/colloquium-schedule-2015-2016&quot;&gt;weekly colloquium series of the Federated Department of Biology at NJIT and Rutgers-Newark&lt;/a&gt;. See below for the details on David’s talk and a video introducing the theme of his lecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title: Zombie ants: the precise manipulation of animal behavior by a microbe&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When:&lt;/strong&gt; Tuesday, March 29th, 2016 1:00 p.m. – 2:20 p.m.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where:&lt;/strong&gt; NJIT, CENTRAL KING BUILDING, Room 303 (map available &lt;a href=&quot;http://theswarmlab.com/contact/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; One of the most complex examples of parasite control of animal behavior is that of fungi in the genus &lt;em&gt;Ophiocordyceps&lt;/em&gt; controlling ant behavior. In the moments before death the fungus controls the ant to bite into plant tissue providing the parasite a platform to launch spores from the cadaver of the host it will soon kill. In this talk I will discuss our research on this phenomena, examining ultimate and proximate views of why and how animal behavior is controlled by a microbe. We work from the micron scale as fungi surround and invade ant muscles to the continental scale as fungi evolve in to control ants in the context of past climatic change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;position: relative; width: 100%; height: 0; padding-bottom: 61%;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe style=&quot;position: absolute; width: 100%; height: 100%; left: 0; top: 0;&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/XuKjBIBBAL8&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 28 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/2016/03/28/David-Hughes-lecture/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/2016/03/28/David-Hughes-lecture/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>videoplayR v0.3 is out!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The people who know me a bit are very much aware of the fact that I am an avid &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.r-project.org&quot;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt; user AND proselyte. I perform all my data processing and visualization in R; I write reports and presentations in R; I even write R packages just for the pleasure of doing it (for instance, I created the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/swarm-lab/editR&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;editR&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; package essentially to see how easy it would be to build a complete web-application with R. Hint: it’s not as hard as I thought it would be).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While R is serving me very well, it always had one big limitation: it cannot process videos. This forced me to use Matlab (ew!) to develop computer vision scripts and applications for processing the videos from our behavioral experiments. Now, I do not have anything against Matlab in particular (besides the fact that it is ridiculously expensive), but I would rather keep my entire data processing workflow within R as much as possible, which meant that I had to either wait for someone to finally develop a computer vision library for R, or develop it myself. And so, this is how &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/swarm-lab/videoplayR&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;videoplayR&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; came to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/2015-09-10-videoplayR-v0.3-is-out/tracks.png&quot; alt=&quot;Trajectories of three ants tracked with `videoplayR`&quot; class=&quot;wrap-around-right&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;videoplayR&lt;/code&gt; is an embryo of a computer vision library for R. It is built upon a powerful C++ image and video processing library called &lt;a href=&quot;http://opencv.org/&quot;&gt;OpenCV&lt;/a&gt;. I used the fantastic &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rcpp.org/&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Rcpp&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; suite of R packages to interface &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;OpenCV&lt;/code&gt; with R. And it’s working! For instance, I managed to create and run successfully a basic particle tracker on one of our ant videos. You can see the result in the screen capture on the right. The software detected and tracked the three ants in the video (technically, there are 5 ants in this video, but 2 of them never moved). It’s all done with a few lines of R code thanks to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;videoplayR&lt;/code&gt;. If you want to see for yourself how easy it is to use &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;videoplayR&lt;/code&gt;, you can play with the different examples in the package vignette that I made available on &lt;a href=&quot;http://rpubs.com/&quot;&gt;Rpubs&lt;/a&gt; at: &lt;a href=&quot;http://rpubs.com/sjmgarnier/videoplayR&quot;&gt;http://rpubs.com/sjmgarnier/videoplayR&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not perfect yet. It’s lacking a lot of basic and advanced features that are normally found in a full-fledged computer vision library. It requires the installation of OpenCV, which is fairly standardized on Mac (thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;http://brew.sh/&quot;&gt;Homebrew&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.macports.org/&quot;&gt;MacPorts&lt;/a&gt;) and Linux, but not so much on Windows. Because of that, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;videoplayR&lt;/code&gt; is not (yet) available on Windows, and is unlikely to end up on &lt;a href=&quot;https://cran.r-project.org/&quot;&gt;CRAN&lt;/a&gt; anytime soon, unless someone with a lot more experience than me can figure out how to ship OpenCV alongside &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;videoplayR&lt;/code&gt; in a way that can compile (I tried, I failed). All the functions could probably be more optimized, but that too will require the help of a C++ guru.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However what is currently available in the package works, and it works pretty well. I believe that it is intuitive enough for most people to get started with image and video processing with R. And it is fairly fast; I have created a basic particle detector that ran at about 21 images per second on my laptop with HD videos. This number can certainly be improved, but it is not bad at all for a first try. I will keep improving it over time following the needs of my laboratory, but I welcome comments, bug reports and feature requests - or, better, pull requests - that can be made directly on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/&quot;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt; repository of the package at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/swarm-lab/videoplayR&quot;&gt;https://github.com/swarm-lab/videoplayR&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;I should mention that I am certainly not the only R user who is desperate enough to have developed a computer vision library for his favorite language. A number of packages have been created to read, process and write images with R. For instance, you can find the  &lt;a href=&quot;http://bioconductor.org/packages/release/bioc/html/EBImage.html&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;EBImage&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; package on BioConductor, or the &lt;a href=&quot;https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/ripa/ripa.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ripa&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; package on CRAN. However good these two packages are at processing images (they are very good), they cannot read videos, which is deal breaker for me.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Very recently, a new package called &lt;a href=&quot;http://dahtah.github.io/imager/&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;imager&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; has been released that is capable of reading videos. It is a fantastic package with a lot of very well thought out functions that I recommend you try. However it has the big disadvantage of loading all the frames of a video directly in R’s memory, making it virtually unusable with the large HD videos that we are used to handle in the laboratory. The same developer also released an experimental package called &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/dahtah/imagerstreams&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;imagerstreams&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; that is capable of performing “out-of-R-memory” video processing using OpenCV, like &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;videoplayR&lt;/code&gt;. But a few tests showed that it was not capable of very high processing speeds with HD videos (about 4.5 times slower than &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;videoplayR&lt;/code&gt;). However I am in contact with the developer to find a way to make &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;videoplayR&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;imager&lt;/code&gt; talk to each other in order to offer R users the best experience possible when developing computer vision software with R.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 10 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/r/2015/09/10/videoplayR-v0.3-is-out/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/r/2015/09/10/videoplayR-v0.3-is-out/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
        <category>r</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Richard Feynman had a thing for ants</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;wrap-around-right&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/4/42/Richard_Feynman_Nobel.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Portrait of Richard Feynman - © The Nobel Foundation, 1965.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Portrait of Richard Feynman - © The Nobel Foundation, 1965&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today is the day &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Project_Grunt&quot;&gt;Lisa&lt;/a&gt; flies to Africa for a couple months of field work. Among 
other things she will outfit local goats with GPS collars coupled with small microphones, that she just spent a month 
and a half patiently building in Swansea, where the &lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/site/andrewjkingresearch/&quot;&gt;SHOAL group&lt;/a&gt; of 
our collaborator &lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/site/andrewjkingresearch/groupmembers/CV&quot;&gt;Andrew King&lt;/a&gt; resides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While in the train toward London Heathrow, she overheard a dad reading a story to his son, a story about ants. Out of 
curiosity, I asked her to enquire about the book the story was coming from. I was expecting some sort of children book,
but was surprised to hear that it was actually “Surely You’re Joking, Mr. Feynman!”, a collection of anecdotes told by 
world famous physicist &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Feynman&quot;&gt;Richard Feynman&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I immediately fired up Google and quickly found the full text on &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.com/books?id=7papZR4oVssC&amp;amp;lpg=PP1&quot;&gt;Google Books&lt;/a&gt;. 
A few more clicks and here it was, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.com/books?id=7papZR4oVssC&amp;amp;lpg=PP1&amp;amp;pg=PA93#v=onepage&amp;amp;q&amp;amp;f=false&quot;&gt;story of Richard Feynman and the ants&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that Feynman loved watching bugs, and ants in particular, and that he used is free time while at Princeton,
and later Caltech, to perform simple experiments with them, in order to understand how ants navigate their environment. 
Isn’t it great?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hereafter is one of these experiments, as told by Feynman himself. It is my favorite one, mostly because it ties in some
work that we are currently doing in the lab. I hope you enjoy it as much as I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Many years later, when I was at Caltech and lived in a little house on Alameda Street, some ants came out around the 
bathtub. I thought, “This is a great opportunity.” I put some sugar on the other end of the bathtub, and sat there 
the whole afternoon until an ant finally found the sugar. It’s only a question of patience.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The moment the ant found the sugar, I picked up a colored pencil that I had ready (I had previously done experiments 
indicating that the ants don’t give a damn about pencil marks – they walk right over them – so I knew I wasn’t 
disturbing anything), and behind where the ant went I drew a line so I could tell where his trail was. The ant 
wandered a little bit wrong to get back to the hole, so the line was quite wiggly, unlike a typical ant trail.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;When the next ant to find the sugar began to go back, I marked his trail with another color. (By the way, he 
followed the first ant’s return trail back, rather than his own incoming trail. My theory is that when an ant has 
found some food, he leaves a much stronger trail than when he’s just wandering around.)&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;This second ant was in a great hurry and followed, pretty much, the original trail. But because he was going so 
fast he would go straight out, as if he were coasting, when the trail was wiggly. Often, as the ant was “coasting,” 
he would find the trail again. Already it was apparent that the second ant’s return was slightly straighter. With 
successive ants the same “improvement” of the trail by hurriedly and carelessly “following” it occurred.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I followed eight or ten ants with my pencil until their trails became a neat line right along the bathtub. It’s 
something like sketching: You draw a lousy line at first; then you go over it a few times and it makes a nice
line after a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 08 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/2015/08/08/Richard-Feynman-had-a-thing-for-ants/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/2015/08/08/Richard-Feynman-had-a-thing-for-ants/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
