<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Swarm Lab</title>
    <description>Welcome to the Swarm Lab where we study Swarm Intelligence in natural and artificial systems.</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Tue, 21 May 2019 18:08:20 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 21 May 2019 18:08:20 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.7.4</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Feature in The New York Times</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The SwarmLab was featured today in a New York Times article by &lt;a href=&quot;https://joshuasokol.com/&quot;&gt;Joshua Sokol&lt;/a&gt; discussing the science fiction myth that disabling the “queen” of a swarm will immediately lead its collapse (it doesn’t!). You can read it all in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2019/05/14/science/hives-queens-science-fiction.html&quot;&gt;“Striking Down the Queen Won’t Save You From the Swarm”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 14 May 2019 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/05/14/new-york-times/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/05/14/new-york-times/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>New publication - &quot;Contact Calls Facilitate Group Contraction in Free-ranging Goats (&lt;i&gt;Capra aegagrus hircus&lt;/i&gt;)&quot;</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The SwarmLab is happy to announce the publication of: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fevo.2019.00073/&quot;&gt;O’Bryan, L., Abaid, N., Nakayama, S., Dey, T., King, A., Cowlishaw, G., et al. (2019). Contact Calls Facilitate Group Contraction in Free-ranging Goats (Capra aegagrus hircus). Frontiers in Ecology and Evolution 7, 73. doi:10.3389/fevo.2019.00073&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many social animal species produce vocalizations believed to facilitate group contraction when one or more group members have become distant. However, the mechanisms underlying this function remain unclear for many species. We examined this question with data on a semi-free ranging group of 16 adult domesticated goats (&lt;em&gt;Capra aegagrus hircus&lt;/em&gt;) inhabiting Tsaobis Nature Park, Namibia. All goats wore dataloggers consisting of a GPS and audio recorder for 5-6 hours per day for 10 days, providing continuous data on their geolocations and vocal communication. We found that callers were farther from the group centroid than expected by chance and that call production was associated with the cessation of group expansion and subsequent group contraction. We did not find strong evidence for antiphonal call exchange between distant and core group members. Rather, we found that (i) call production by distant group members is associated with a significant reduction of group movement away from the caller, and (ii) call production by core group members is associated with greater, though not significantly greater, group movement towards the caller. These findings suggest that calls may be used by distant, and potentially core, group members to facilitate the contraction of group spread. Results from our study clarify the mechanisms through which social animals can regulate collective movement behavior and the specific role that vocalizations play in this process.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2019 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/03/19/new-publication/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/03/19/new-publication/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>New publication - &quot;Information Transfer During Food Choice in the Slime Mold &lt;i&gt;Physarum polycephalum&lt;/i&gt;&quot;</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The SwarmLab is happy to announce the publication of: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fevo.2019.00067/&quot;&gt;Ray, S., Valentini, G., Shah, P., Haque, A., Reid, C., Weber, G., et al. (2019). Information Transfer During Food Choice in the Slime Mold Physarum polycephalum. Frontiers in Ecology and Evolution 7, 67. doi:10.3389/fevo.2019.00067&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This paper is a first publication for Subash, Purva and Abid. Many congratulations to them!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout evolution, living systems have developed mechanisms to make adaptive decisions in the face of complex and changing environmental conditions. Most organisms make such decisions despite lacking a neural architecture. This is the case of the acellular slime mold &lt;em&gt;Physarum polycephalum&lt;/em&gt; that has demonstrated remarkable information processing and problem-solving abilities. Previous studies suggest that the membrane of &lt;em&gt;P. polycephalum&lt;/em&gt; plays an important role in integrating and processing information leading to the selection of a resource to exploit. The cyclical contraction-relaxation pattern of the membrane changes with the local quality of the environment, and individual contractile regions within a &lt;em&gt;P. polycephalum&lt;/em&gt; can entrain neighboring regions, providing a potential mechanism for information processing and propagation. In this study, we use an information-theoretic tool, transfer entropy, to study the flow of information in single tubule segments of &lt;em&gt;P. polycephalum&lt;/em&gt; in a binary choice between two food sources. We test &lt;em&gt;P. polycephalum&lt;/em&gt; tubules in two food choice conditions, where the two available options are either symmetric in their nutrient concentrations or with one more concentrated in nutrients than the other (i.e., asymmetric). We measure the contractile pattern of the &lt;em&gt;P. polycephalum&lt;/em&gt; membrane and use these data to explore the direction and amount of information transfer along the tubule as a function of the cell’s final decision. We find that the direction of information transfer is different in the two experimental conditions, and the amount of information transferred is inversely proportional to the distance between different contractile regions. Our results show that regions playing a leading role in information transfer changes with the decision-making challenges faced by &lt;em&gt;P. polycephalum&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2019 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/03/14/new-publication2/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/03/14/new-publication2/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>New publication - &quot;Temporal and spatial pattern of trail clearing in the Australian meat ant, &lt;i&gt;Iridomyrmex purpureus&lt;/i&gt;&quot;</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The SwarmLab is happy to announce the publication of: &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.anbehav.2019.02.006&quot;&gt;Middleton, E. J. T., Garnier, S., Latty, T., and Reid, C. R. (2019). Temporal and spatial pattern of trail clearing in the Australian meat ant, &lt;em&gt;Iridomyrmex purpureus&lt;/em&gt;. Anim. Behav. 150, 97–111. doi:10.1016/j.anbehav.2019.02.006&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; Many ant species use trails to connect important resources. In addition, some ants actively clear obstacles from their trails. Although trail clearing is thought to be beneficial in decreasing travel time, the physical process of clearing requires an investment of time and energy. Given that trail clearing is a decentralized process, how do colonies decide when to invest in clearing? In this study, we examined trail clearing in the Australian meat ant, using artificial semipermeable barriers mimicking grass. We tested the hypothesis that investment in clearing was influenced by the abundance and physical toughness of obstacles and that the selection of which grass blade to cut was a nonrandom process that decreases travel distance. We found that low abundance/low toughness treatments experienced the greatest amount of clearing and high abundance/high toughness the least. Although ants did not clear an optimally efficient trail, the results of our percolation analysis support the inference that the ants strategically deployed clearing, taking multiple factors into account when deciding to invest in this strategy. The resultant clearing patterns provided shorter travel routes for foraging ants than would be expected by the random removal of obstacles.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2019 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/03/09/new-publication/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/03/09/new-publication/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Announcing the 4th Collaborative Workshop on Modeling Collective Behavior</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The SwarmLab is pleased to announce the 4th Collaborative Workshop on Modeling Collective Behavior, funded by the NSF OAC Public Access Initiative &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nsf.gov/awardsearch/showAward?AWD_ID=1838955&quot;&gt;grant #1838955&lt;/a&gt;. The goal of this workshop is to provide researchers coming from mathematics, physics, engineering and biology with experience in working collaboratively to model and analyze data produced by research in collective behavior. This year we are also including an interdisciplinary art/science project (see Project 4 below) that will use virtual reality to explore and interact with data and models of collective behaviors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All information about the workshop, including application instructions and deadline, can be found &lt;a href=&quot;/meetings/data_model_2019/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/data_model_2019/banner.png&quot; alt=&quot;banner&quot; class=&quot;full&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2019 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/03/01/data-model-2019/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/03/01/data-model-2019/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Data-Driven Modeling of Collective Behavior and Emergent Phenomena in Biology (DDM-Bio) - June 5-7, 2017</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The SwarmLab is happy to announce the workshop on “Data-Driven Modeling of Collective Behavior and Emergent Phenomena in Biology” (&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/search?q=%23DDMBio&amp;amp;src=typd&quot;&gt;#DDMBio&lt;/a&gt;) to be held at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.samsi.info/&quot;&gt;SAMSI&lt;/a&gt; (Research Triangle Park, NC), June 5-7, 2017.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Description&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Collective behavior and emergent phenomena often arise in complex adaptive systems. Understanding the mechanisms that underlie such processes is simultaneously challenging and important to developments in engineering, technology, and advancing basic knowledge in the science of biological systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This collaborative workshop is targeted for researchers and students with research interests in collective behavior and emergent phenomena in biology and its applications. The participants will be organized into interdisciplinary teams according to their interests and complementary skills. Each team will be tasked with exploring, analyzing and modeling original data sets provided by biologist attendees. The event will be similar in spirit to a hackathon in computer science, with the goal of finding new ways to understand the provided biological data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We emphasize that the workshop is meant to involve active participation with attendees working together across disciplines to solve problems in current research. In addition, regular debriefing sessions will be organized throughout the 3 days of the workshop in order for each team to provide updates to and receive feedback from the rest of the participants on their progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Organizing Committee:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://theswarmlab.com/&quot;&gt;Simon Garnier&lt;/a&gt;, Dept. of Biological Sciences, New Jersey Institute of Technology&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/site/jasonmgrahamus/&quot;&gt;Jason M. Graham&lt;/a&gt;, Dept. of Mathematics, University of Scranton**&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;application-information&quot;&gt;Application information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://duke.qualtrics.com/SE/?SID=SV_eyaNrivpvY48fv7&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; class=&quot;btn btn-info&quot; role=&quot;button&quot;&gt;Apply Here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Application Deadline is April 17, 2017.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The workshop will be limited to about 40 participants and funding support priority will be given to U.S. based researchers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Questions: &lt;a href=&quot;ddm-bio@samsi.info&quot;&gt;ddm-bio@samsi.info&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 14 Dec 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/2016/12/14/DDM-Bio/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/2016/12/14/DDM-Bio/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>We're Hiring! Tenure track position in &quot;Organismic Function, from Behavior to Ecology​&quot;</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As part of an ongoing expansion, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://biology.njit.edu/&quot;&gt;Department of Biological Sciences&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.njit.edu&quot;&gt;New Jersey Institute of Technology (NJIT)&lt;/a&gt; is looking to fill one or two new tenure-track faculty positions at the Assistant Professor level, beginning in 2017. We seek applicants with an interest and established record in bridging levels from systems or organismic function to behavior or ecology. Research areas can include - but are not limited to - ethology, microbiology, functional ecology, or evolution. Candidates will be expected to maintain an active, funded research program, supervise graduate students, and contribute to the overall success of the Department.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NJIT is a tier-one public research university located in Newark, NJ, with an emphasis on STEM subjects. The Department of Biological Sciences at NJIT currently consists of ten research faculty with expertise in neurobiology, sensory and motor systems, locomotion, collective behavior, and functional and spatial ecology. The Department is also Federated with neighboring &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncas.rutgers.edu/biology&quot;&gt;Rutgers-University Newark&lt;/a&gt;, adding colleagues in cellular neurobiology, cell signaling, genetics, systematics, evolution and ecology. The successful applicant will occupy customizable space in a newly renovated research facility. Duties will also include teaching introductory and upper-level undergraduate and graduate courses, depending on expertise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NJIT is an equal-opportunity employer. Applications from minorities and women are especially welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Applicants should upload a CV, a cover letter, and a statement of research interest at the following address: &lt;a href=&quot;http://njit.jobs/applicants/Central?quickFind=55733&quot;&gt;njit.jobs/applicants/Central?quickFind=55733&lt;/a&gt;. In addition, they should arrange for at least three references to send letters directly to Ms. Shamay Carty at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:carty@njit.edu&quot;&gt;carty@njit.edu&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All inquiries should be directed to Dr. Simon Garnier, at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:garnier@njit.edu&quot;&gt;garnier@njit.edu&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/2016/10/05/We-re-hiring/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/2016/10/05/We-re-hiring/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>We're Hiring! Tenure track position in &quot;Cell Biology, Physiology, Systems or Organismic Function​&quot;</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As part of an ongoing expansion, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://biology.njit.edu/&quot;&gt;Department of Biological Sciences&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.njit.edu&quot;&gt;New Jersey Institute of Technology (NJIT)&lt;/a&gt; is looking to fill one or two new tenure-track faculty positions at the Assistant Professor level, beginning in 2017. We seek applicants with an interest and established record in bridging levels from cell biology or physiology, to systems or organismic function. Research areas can include - but are not limited to - neurobiology, ethology, evolution, or development. Candidates will be expected to maintain an active, funded research program, supervise graduate students, and contribute to the overall success of the Department.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NJIT is a tier-one public research university located in Newark, NJ, with an emphasis on STEM subjects. The Department of Biological Sciences at NJIT currently consists of ten research faculty with expertise in neurobiology, sensory and motor systems, locomotion, collective behavior, and functional and spatial ecology. The Department is also Federated with neighboring &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncas.rutgers.edu/biology&quot;&gt;Rutgers-University Newark&lt;/a&gt;, adding colleagues in cellular neurobiology, cell signaling, genetics, systematics, evolution and ecology. The successful applicant will occupy customizable space in a newly renovated research facility. Duties will also include teaching introductory and upper-level undergraduate and graduate courses, depending on expertise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NJIT is an equal-opportunity employer. Applications from minorities and women are especially welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Applicants should upload a CV, a cover letter, and a statement of research interest at the following address: &lt;a href=&quot;http://njit.jobs/applicants/Central?quickFind=55732&quot;&gt;njit.jobs/applicants/Central?quickFind=55732&lt;/a&gt;. In addition, they should arrange for at least three references to send letters directly to Ms. Shamay Carty at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:carty@njit.edu&quot;&gt;carty@njit.edu&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All inquiries should be directed to Dr. Farzan Nadim, at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:farzan@njit.edu&quot;&gt;farzan@njit.edu&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/2016/10/05/We-re-hiring-2/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/2016/10/05/We-re-hiring-2/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Decision-making without a brain - Our new paper in Interface</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;How do organisms without brains make decisions? Most of life is brainless and the vast majority of organisms on Earth lack neurons altogether. Plants, fungi and bacteria must all cope with the same problem as humans – to make the best choices in a complex and ever-changing world or risk dying – without the help of a simple nervous system in many cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our lab in collaboration with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.richardpmann.com/&quot;&gt;Richard Mann&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.leeds.ac.uk/&quot;&gt;University of Leeds&lt;/a&gt;), &lt;a href=&quot;http://staffwww.dcs.shef.ac.uk/people/J.Marshall/james.html&quot;&gt;James Marshall&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sheffield.ac.uk/&quot;&gt;University of Sheffield&lt;/a&gt;) and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tanyalatty.com/&quot;&gt;Tanya Latty&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;http://sydney.edu.au/&quot;&gt;University of Sydney&lt;/a&gt;) recently studied this problem in the unicellular slime mold, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Physarum_polycephalum&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Physarum polycephalum&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a single-cell organism that can grow to several square meters in size. This giant cell, which typically lives in shady, cool and moist areas of temperate forests, spreads out to search its environment like an amoeba, extending oozy tendrils along the forest floor in search of its prey of fungi, bacteria and decaying vegetable matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neither plant, animal nor fungus, &lt;em&gt;P. polycephalum&lt;/em&gt; has become an unlikely candidate for studies of cognition, due to its spectacular problem-solving abilities. In recent studies, &lt;em&gt;Physarum&lt;/em&gt; has been shown to solve labyrinth mazes, make complicated trade-offs, anticipate periodic events, remember where it has been, construct transport networks that have similar efficiency to those designed by human engineers and even make irrational decisions – a capability that has long been viewed as a by-product of brain circuitry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this study, we examined the decision-making ability of slime mold using a test classically used in humans, birds and other brained organisms: the two-armed bandit problem, named for the infamous slot machine, or one-armed bandit. In a two-armed bandit problem, the subject has two levers to pull, each of which delivers a certain, randomly determined reward. One of the levers is more likely to deliver a higher reward overall, so the challenge for participants is to decide at what point to stop exploring both options and decide to exclusively exploit just the one option in order to maximize their payoff. The phenomenon is called the exploration-exploitation tradeoff and is relevant to more than just slot machines, applying to many situations, including investors picking start-up companies to back or drivers choosing a parking space. As such, it has become a classical tool for testing the decision-making abilities of humans and other animals, but it has never before been used on an organism without a brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We adapted the two-armed bandit test for slime mold by giving the organism the choice to explore two opposite directions. In each direction, the slime mold encountered discrete patches of food, more or less regularly distributed. One direction would contain more of these patches than the other. They then observed how far in each direction the slime mold would explore before switching to the exploitation of one of the two directions only. The results of these experiments demonstrate that slime mold compares the relative qualities of multiple options, most often choosing the direction with the higher overall concentration of food. It was able to sum up the number of food patches encountered in each direction, as well as the quantity of food present at each patch to make correct and adaptive decisions as to the direction it should move next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The slime mold’s decision-making algorithm can be mathematically described as a tendency to exploit environments in proportion to their reward experienced through past sampling. The algorithm is intermediate in computational complexity between simple, reactionary heuristics and calculation-intensive optimal performance algorithms, yet it has very good relative performance. While the biological substrate of the algorithm remains to be identified, this study provides insight into ancestral mechanisms of decision making and suggests that fundamental principles of decision making, information processing and even cognition are shared among diverse biological systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our study has appeared in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://rsif.royalsocietypublishing.org/content/13/119&quot;&gt;June edition&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://rsif.royalsocietypublishing.org/&quot;&gt;Journal of The Royal Society Interface&lt;/a&gt; and can be found &lt;a href=&quot;http://rsif.royalsocietypublishing.org/content/13/119/20160030&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;in open access&lt;/strong&gt; here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 19 Jun 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/2016/06/19/Decision-Making-Without-Brain/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/2016/06/19/Decision-Making-Without-Brain/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Lens of Time - Slime Lapse</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Our work on slime mold was recently featured in a mini-documentary by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.spinefilms.com/&quot;&gt;Spine Films&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;a href=&quot;http://biographic.com/&quot;&gt;bioGraphic&lt;/a&gt;, a new multimedia magazine produced by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.calacademy.org/&quot;&gt;California Academy of Sciences&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;video width=&quot;100%&quot; controls=&quot;controls&quot;&gt;
  &lt;source src=&quot;http://n2ps.storied.co/uploads/548ceb34b78402c4c1baadd636a132f4.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/video&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jun 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/2016/06/12/Lens-of-Time-Slime-Lapse/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/2016/06/12/Lens-of-Time-Slime-Lapse/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
